Guide to the Mary Bridges-Adams Collection on British Labour Movement and Russian Socialists,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Mary Bridges-Adams Collection on British Labour Movement and Russian Socialists,
1905-1939.
Bridges-Adams, Mary
3 linear ft. (3 document boxes, 1 oversized flat box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
BA#0534
9135518
The collection of letters and documents addressed to, or relating to, Mrs. Mary Jane Bridges-Adams (1854–1939), British socialist and educationist, in connection with the British Labour movement and with the Russian Political Prisoners and Exiles Relief Committee in London. The collection also includes letters and documents of Georgii Chicherin (1872-1936), Russian diplomat, revolutionary, and second Commissar of Foreign Affairs, concerning his activities in London and Europe.
Biographical Note
Mary Jane Bridges-Adams (née Daltry, 1854–1939), left-wing socialist especially interested in educational matters, a leading propagandist of educational reform, was born on October 19, 1854 at Maesycwmer, Bedwas, Monmouthshire, south Wales.
She was a member of the London School Board (1897-1903) and stood for free, compulsory education, for a secular curriculum, and for equal educational opportunity; a member of the Woolwich branch of the Women's Co-operative Guild (1890s); an honorary member of an association of trade union officials to facilitate the exchange of information on the legal position of trade unions. Bridges-Adams was involved with the Froebel movement. In 1901, Mary Bridges-Adams initiated the foundation of the National Labour Education League. She became a close friend of the Countess of Warwick and as her secretary and collaborator ran a London-based office and discussion centre, visitors to which included Gorst, Thorne, and Winston Churchill. Among her achievements was the establishment of the first Open Air School for Recovery in Bostall Woods, owned by the Royal Arsenal Co-operative Society. In 1909 she concentrated on adult education and in 1912 began a campaign to establish a working women's labour college. A year later she established a Working Women's Movement.
In 1914, Mary Bridges-Adams joined the political fight to preserve the right of asylum enjoyed by refugees from tsarist Russia, among whom was Georgii Chicherin, a future Soviet foreign minister. She became a proactive member of the Russian Political Prisoners and Exiles Relief Committee in London. Mary Bridges-Adams died at Princess Beatrice Hospital, London, on January 14, 1939.
Georgii Vasil'evich Chicherin, (born November 24, 1872, Tambov province, Russia - died July 7, 1936, Moscow), Russian diplomat, revolutionary and later second Commissar of Foreign Affairs, who led Soviet foreign policy from 1918 until 1928.
An aristocrat by birth, Chicherin entered the imperial diplomatic service after graduating from the University of St. Petersburg (1897). He became involved in the Russian revolutionary movement, however, and in 1904 resigned his post, renounced title to his estates, and went to Berlin, where he joined the Menshevik faction of the Russian Social Democratic Party (1905). For the next 12 years he devoted himself to party activities, working closely with the French Socialists and the British labour movement.
During World War I he took part in pacifist and relief activities in London organizing aid for revolutionaries under the relief committee, in which he was aided by Mary Bridges-Adams, and later for the Delegation of Russian Socialist Groups in London. After the Bolsheviks seized power in Russia in 1917, the British arrested him and, in exchange for their ambassador, Sir George Buchanan, released him on January 3, 1918. Chicherin returned to Russia and joined the Bolshevik Party. He then resumed his diplomatic career, participating in the final stage of negotiating the Brest-Litovsk peace treaty with Germany and subsequently becoming People’s commissar for foreign affairs (May 1918). After negotiating treaties resolving territorial and commercial disputes, Chicherin headed the Soviet delegation to the conference of European nations held at Genoa to consider reconstruction of the European economy (1922). There he secretly negotiated the Treaty of Rapallo with Germany (signed April 16, 1922), which established normal commercial and diplomatic relations between the two countries and thereby ended the diplomatic and economic isolation that had been imposed on Russia and Germany after World War I. Although he had little influence in determining the foreign policies of the Soviet Union, Chicherin continued to carry them out skillfully until illness prevented him from performing his duties in 1928; he retired in 1930.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of Mary Bridges-Adams and Georgii Chicherin materials. The Bridges-Adams papers contain correspondence and documents related to her activity as a labour movement activist and to the Russian Political Prisoners and Exiles Relief Committee in London, the revolutionary movement in Russia, the campaign against repatriation and the right of asylum, and social and educational matters. The correspondence contains letters from prominent people, such as Winston Churchill, Georgii Chicherin, Sir Victor Horsley, Henry Mayers Hyndman, Aleksandra Kollontai, Maksim Litvinov, Edward Lyulph Stanley (Fourth Baron Sheffield), Frances Evelyn Maynard Greville, Countess of Warwick. The remainder of the correspondence includes letters from socialist individuals and organizations. There are also some of Bridges-Adams' writings, printed ephemera, newspaper clippings, and other related materials.
The Chicherin papers mostly contain materials related to the time of his emigration and his life in Great Britain. There is correspondence, drafts and copies of speeches and articles, reports, minutes of meetings, accounts for various activities, notes, a few documents related to his deportation, and printed ephemera and newspaper clippings. Chicherin corresponded with a number of prominent people including Robert Applegarth, Sergei Bagotskii, Fenner Brockway, Fedor Dan, Aleksandra Kollontai, A. Lozovskii, Iulii Martov, S. Semkovskii, Philip Snowden.
Oversize materials have been separated and stored in Flat box #4 of the Bakhmeteff Archive Flat box collection. References are provided.
There are cross-references provided throughout the finding aid. When the cross-reference refers to another item within the same series, the reference includes the specific name or title and box and folder number (this also applies to the references within same subseries). If the cross-reference is to an item in another series, the reference includes the series number, series name, folder title, and box and folder numbers (this also applies to references to the items in another subseries).
Arrangement
This collection is organized in two series:
Series I: Mary Bridges-Adams Materials, 1905-1939,undated
Subseries I.1: Correspondence, 1905-1939, undated
Subseries I.2: Writings, 1915, undated
Subseries I.3: Documents and Printed Materials, 1908-1917, undated
Series II: Georgii Checherin Materials, 1908-1918, undated
Subseries II.1: Correspondence, 1912-1917, undated
Subseries II.2: Writings and Research Materials, 1914-1916, undated
Subseries II.3: Documents and Contacts, 1908-1917, undated
Subseries II.4: Activity in various organizations, 1914-1917
Subseries II.5: Printed Materials, 1915-1918, undated
Subjects
Rossiiskaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia rabochaia partiia.; Applegarth, Robert, 1834-1924.; Bagotskii, S. (Sergei), 1879-1953.; Brockway, Fenner, 1888-1988.; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965; Chicherin, G. (Georgii), 1872-1936.; Dan, F. (Fedor), 1871-1947.; Horsley, Victor, Sir, 1857-1916.; Hyndman, H. M. (Henry Mayers), 1842-1921.; Kollontai, A. (Aleksandra), 1872-1952.; Litvinov, M. M. (Maksim Maksimovich), 1876-1951.; Lozovskii, A., 1878-1952.; Martov, L., 1873-1923.; Semkovskii, S.; Snowden, Philip Snowden, Viscount, 1864-1937.; Stanley, Edward Lyulph, 1839-1925.; Warwick, Frances Evelyn Maynard Greville, Countess of, 1861-1938.; Education--Great Britain.; Labour Party (Great Britain).; Political activists--Great Britain.; Russians--Great Britain--Politics and government.; Socialist Movement (Great Britain).; Socialists--Great Britain.; Women political activists--Great Britain.; Women socialists--Great Britain.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Documents.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Purchase 1993
- Series I: Mary Bridges-Adams Materials, 1905-1939, undated
  The series consists of Mary Bridges-Adams's correspondence, documents, writings, printed ephemera, and newspaper clippings. Organized in three subseries.
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence, 1905-1939, undated
    Contains Bridges-Adams' correspondence with various people and organizations in connection with her labour movement and socialist activity, and to Russians in exile and particularly to the Russian Political Prisoners and Exiles Relief Committee in London. Also included are a few letters to Frances Evelyn Maynard Greville Warwick from other people. Series subdivided by subject: correspondence with prominent people, general correspondence with individuals, correspondence with organizations, and outgoing letters. Letters arranged alphabetically within each subject of the subseries.
    - Correspondence with Prominent People, 1905-1925 undated:
      - Churchill, Winston, to Frances Evelyn Maynard Greville Warwick, May 27, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        (1 autograph letter signed "W")
      - Chicherin, Georgii, to Mary Bridges-Adams, various places, 1907-1921, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
        (3 autograph letters signed, 1 autograph note signed, 1 telegram)
      - Horsley, Victor, Sir, to Mary Bridges-Adams, Norwich, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        (2 autograph letters signed; 1 Mary Bridges-Adams's draft of reply)
      - Hyndman, Henry Mayers:
        - To Mary Bridges-Adams, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
          (2 autograph letters signed)
        - To Frances Evelyn Maynard Greville Warwick, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 4)
          (1 autograph letter signed)
      - Kollontai, Aleksandra, to Mary Bridges-Adams, [1925] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Litvinov, Maksim Maksimovich, to Mary Bridges-Adams, London, July 9, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        (1 typed letter signed)
      - Stanley, Edward Lyulph (Baron Sheffield), to Mary Bridges-Adams, various places, 1918-1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        (18 autograph letters signed)
      - Warwick, Frances Evelyn Maynard Greville, Countess:
        - To Mary Bridges-Adams, various places, 1903-1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
          (20 autograph letters signed, 1 telegram)
        - To Willy, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Lily to Frances Evelyn Warwick, Dresden, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Blumenfeld, Ralph D. to Frances Evelyn Warwick, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
          (handwritten copy by Mary Bridges-Adams)
    - General Correspondence with Individuals, 1906-1939
      - Baldwin, F., Paddington, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Blatchford, Robert Peel Granville, London, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Brailsford, Henry Noel, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Cox, Alfred, 1907, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Faulkner, Ernest J.: see Westcotes Ward Independent Labour Party (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Fridolin, Vladimir, Paris, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Jones, Margaret, Oxford, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        (Bridges-Adams' mother)
      - King, Joseph, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Nevinson, Henry Woodd, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Smith, Frank, London, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Snowden, Ethel, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Unidentified, 1906-1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Envelopes, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with Organizations, 1907-1926
      - Central Information Bureau (London Women's Peace Crusade): see General Correspondence with Individuals--Snowden, Ethel (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Central Labour College, London, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Clarion: Newspaper Company, Ltd.: see Blatchford, R. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Embassy of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, London, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Gorton United Trades & Labour Council, Gorton, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - National Council for Civil Liberties, London, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Polnomochnoe predstavitel'stvo SSSR v Velikobritanii: see Embassy of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
      - Social-Democratic Federation (Social-Democratic Party of Great Britain), London, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Socialist Sunday School, Huddersfield, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Westcotes Ward Independent Labour Party, Leicester, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Worker, Huddersfield, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Outgoing letters, to various people, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries I.2: Writings, 1915, undated
    Comprises a typescript of a memoir note about Georgii Chicherin and his activities in London, articles, and publications.
    - Memoirs about George Chicherin and his activities in London, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      (typescript with holograph notes)
    - "Condemned Denominational Schools in London", [1915] (reprint): see Series: Printed Materials--"Defense of the Realm Acts"
    - Articles and publications:
      - on education, social movement and Labour party, Russia and war, and various subjects: see Subseries I.3: Documents and Printed Materials--Printed Materials
      - on Russian Political Prisoners and Exiles Relief Committee in London: see Series II: Chicherin Papers--Subseries II.4: Activities in various organizations--Russian Political Prisoners and Exiles Relief Committee in London--Printed materials--Clippings (Box 3, Folder 16 and Flat Box #4, Folders 5-6)
  - Subseries I.3: Documents and Printed Materials, 1908-1917, undated
    Contains receipts, resolutions, printed ephemera, and newspaper clippings with materials on education, the situation in Russia, social movement and Labour party.
    - Documents:
      - Receipts and appointment schedule, 1908-1911, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Resolutions and notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Printed Materials
      - Brochures:
        - "Defence of the Realm Acts," London, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 19)
          (reprint. Originally published in Parliamentary debates. House of Lords official report, vol.24, No.II, 401-424)
        - "Russian Refugees and Military Service," London, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 19)
          (reprint. Originally published in Parliamentary debates. House of Lords official report, vol.22, No.60, 983-998)
      - Clippings
        (including Bridges-Adams' articles and publications)
        - On education, 1915, undated
          - Cotton Factory Times, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 1)
            (oversize; stored in Flat Box # 4, Folder 1)
          - Herald (Box 1, Folder 20)
          - Luton News, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - On Russia and the War, 1915
          (oversize; stored in Flat Box # 4, Folders 2-3)
          - Cotton Factory Times, July-November, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 2)
          - Yorkshire Factory Times, October-November, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - On socialist movement and Labour party, 1910s (Box 1, Folder 21)
        - Various, 1973 (Observer Review) (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series II: Georgii Checherin Materials, 1908-1918, undated
  The series comprises correspondence, drafts and copies of speeches and articles, reports, minutes of meetings, accounts for various activities, notes, a few documents related to his deportation, and printed ephemera and newspaper clippings. Most materials are related to the time of Chicherin's emigration and his life in Great Britain. Organized in five subseries.
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence, 1912-1917, undated
    Contains letters of various people and organizations in Russian, English, and French addressed to, or relating to, Chicherin and his efforts to help fellow Russian exiles in Europe and Siberia and to his fundraising activities for RSDRP and exiles relief. Series subdivided by subject: correspondence with prominent people, general correspondence with individuals, correspondence with organizations, outgoing letters, and subject correspondence. Letters arranged alphabetically within each subject of the subseries.
    - Correspondence with Prominent People, 1912-1917 undated:
      - Applegarth, Robert, to George Chicherin, Surrey, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Bagotskii, Sergei Iustinovich, to Georgii Chicherin, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        (8 autograph letters signed, 18 autograph postcards signed, 2 telegrams)
      - Brockway, Fenner, to Bryce Leicester, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Dan, Fedor, to Georgii Chicherin, Paris, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        (1 autograph letter signed by Fedor Dan and Iulii Martov)
      - Kollontai, Aleksandra, to Georgii Chicherin, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
        (autograph letter signed)
      - Lozovskii, A. (pseudonym of Solomon Abramovich Dridzo), to Georgii Chicherin, Paris, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        (2 autograph letters signed, 1 autograph postcard signed)
      - Martov, Iulii: see Dan, Fedor
      - Semkovskii, S.
        (pseudonym of Bronshtein)
        - To Georgii Chicherin, Clarens, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - To Ornatskii, Paris, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - Articles for Nashe slovo (Box 1, Folder 29)
          (2 holograph manuscripts)
      - Snowden, Philip, to Georgii Chicherin, various places, 1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
        (4 typed letters signed, 1 autograph note signed)
    - General correspondence with individuals, 1913-1917 undated:
      - Arkell, A.1917 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Askew, J.B., Golder Green, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Astrov, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Austin Smith, J., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Baldwin, F., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Baldwin, W.M., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Bird, E., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Bennet, L., undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Bobrovnikov, Nikolai and Sonia, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Bond, L., London, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Bracher, S. V., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Brandwood, Harold G., Warrington, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Buv'e, E. (Workers' Suffrage Federation), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Cohen, Max M., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Detprano, Mrs (or Doprano), London, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Dmitrievskii, Viacheslav, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Dolivo-Dobrovol'skii, G. (to K.D. Nabokov): see Subject correspondence (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Dombrovskii, Liverpool, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Eyres, E., Essex, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Field, Arthur, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Fisher, H.M., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Galsky, Anton, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Gompertz, A.E., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Hardy, V.M., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Howe, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Humphrey, A. W., Ashton-under-Lyne, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Khain, B., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - King, James, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Kogan, E., Petrograd, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Laskin, N., London, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Lawrence, J., 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Lewington, A.W.P., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Makushin, V., London, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Maynard, F.J., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Miles, William, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Nalton, Edna, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Newbury, F., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Ozol', Glasgow, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Paul, Cedar, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Petrov, Petr, Glasgow, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 36)
        (see also: Correspondence with Organizations--British Socialist Party, Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Petrova, Irina, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Pettifor, T.C., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Rees, John, Newport, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Rollin, R.undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Satarello, Henri, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Shames, Lev, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Soubrie[?], L., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Stewart, James, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Stiri[?], E., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Stoddart, Ruby, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Surov, D., Paris, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Vainberg, Iulii Stanislavovich, Stockholm, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Weinstein, S., undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Wiltshire, Julia M., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Wynn-Cuthbert, Henri, Worthing, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Unidentified in Russian, 1915-1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
        (some with Chicherin's reply)
      - Unidentified in English and French, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Envelopes, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence with organizations, 1915-1917 undated:
      - Amalgamated Society of Engineers, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Avstraliiskoe obshchestvo pomoshchi politicheskim katorzhanam i ssyl'noposelentsam v Rossii, Brisben, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - British Socialist Party, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Cambridge "Stop-the-War" Committee, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Cardiff Socialist Society, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Central Labour College, London, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Communist Working Men's Club and Institute, Ltd., London, 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Cooperative Printing Society Ltd, London, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Ellis and Co Solicitors, London, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - First of May Celebration Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Fond Russkoi Revoliutsii, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Foreign Jews Protection Committee, against deportation and compuslion, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Fund for the relief of the Jewish Victims of the War in Russia, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Independent Labour Party, 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
        (including printed materials, resolutions, ephemera. Arranged in alphabetical order by the branch name)
      - Kenington and Paddington Labour Council, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Latwijas Social-Demokratija (London Branch), London, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Leicester Labour Party, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Lithuanian Socialist Federation of Great Britain, London, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - London Jewish Tin Plate and Sheet Metal Workers Union, London, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Luton Committee for Anglo-Russian Cooperation, Luton, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - National Amalgamated Furnishing Trades' Association, London, 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - National Amalgamated Union of Shop Assistants, Warehousemen and Clerks, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - National Labour Press Ltd., London, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - National Transport Workers' Federation, London, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - National Union of Clerks, London, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - National Union of Railwaymen, London, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - National Women's Labour League, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - NCF: Ealing Branch, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Neath Socialist Society, Neath Glam, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Nelson, Colne and District Chain Beamers' Association, Nelson, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - No-Conscription Fellowship, Adelphi, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Parti Social-Democrate Ouvrier Russe: see Correspondence with Prominent people--Dan, Fedor (Box, Folder)
      - Russian Political Prisoners and Exiles Relief Committee: see Correspondence with Individuals--Ozol'; Petrov
      - Russkii kruzhok imeni Gertsena, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)